God, that is the most beautiful engagement ring ever!
这真是世上最美的订婚戒指
You should know. You bought, like, a billion of them.
你一定很识货，你买过一大堆
You didn't get one.
但是你没有
-Tonight's the big night. -How you gonna ask her?
-好，就是今晚了  -你要怎么进行？
We're gonna go to her favorite restaurant.
保证完美 我会带她上她最爱的餐厅
I'm gonna get her favorite champagne. She'll know how expensive it is.
我要送她一瓶她很喜欢的香槟 那她就知道有多贵了
When the glasses are full, instead of proposing a toast, I'm gonna propose.
然后等酒斟好了，我不会敬酒 我会向她求婚
It sounds perfect!
好棒喔
-You'll mess it up. Let me do it. -I won't mess it up.
-你会搞砸 让我来吧  -我才不会搞砸
-lf she says no,can I have the ring? -She won't say no.
-要是她说不，戒指可以给我吗  -她不会说不
If.
要是
-Sure. -What about me? I want it too.
-没问题  -那我呢？我也想要
-She won't say no. -I'll let you borrow it.
-她不会说不  -我再借给你
Hey,Monica.
-Give it. -It's gone.
-还给我 -吞下去了
Phoebe.
菲比
Hey,Monica!
We're practically kissing.
我们在接吻喔
The One With the Proposal
本集播出：“惊喜的求婚”
rainystar压制iPod-MP4
Anyone free tonight? My boss is hosting a charity event for kids.
晚上有人有空吗？ 我主管要主持救助贫童慈善会
The more people I bring, the better I look. Monica? Chandler?
我带越多人去越有面子 摩妮卡？钱德？
We can't go. We're going to dinner. Remember?
摩妮卡和钱德不能去 我们要去吃饭，记得吗？
-Oh,my God. I'm so sorry. -What's the big deal?
-天哪，真抱歉  -干嘛这么激动？
I get mad when Rachel doesn't remember where we're going.
我只是很气瑞秋不记得 我们要去哪里
Where are you going?
你们要去哪里？
-How about you guys? -Open bar?
-那你们呢？ -酒品免费？
-I think so. -I can do that for the kids.
-应该是  -我可以为孩子们喝酒
I'll come. I'm making money. It's time I give some back.
那我也要去 我现在有收入 也该回馈社会了
You could give back the money you owe me.
你也可以把欠我的钱还给我
Okay. Have a benefit.
好啊，你办义卖啊
Ross, can you go to a charity event tonight?
罗斯 你晚上可以参加慈善晚会吗？
I have plans with Elizabeth.
不行，我跟伊丽莎白有约
You're already doing your part for the kids.
你已经在为孩童贡献心力了
It's our last night before she leaves for camp. To be a counselor.
再过几天她要去夏令营 去当指导员
I have a question. All jokes aside, where is this relationship going?
罗斯 我问你 撇开笑话不提 这段感情要往哪里走？
All jokes aside? I didn't agree to that.
等等，撇开笑话不提？ 我可不同意
-Do you see this as long-term? -I don't know.
-你认为你们可以长久吗？ -我不知道
-You are 12 years older than her. -Who's counting?
-你比她大12岁喔  -谁会去算？
Well,she is. She's this many.
她会，她才这么大
Ross, she is really young.
罗斯，她真的很年轻
Does everyone feel this way?
等等，你们都这么认为吗？
-Yeah,sort of. -Sorry.
有一点 抱歉
I thought you were just making jokes. I had no idea.
我以为你们只是爱开玩笑 我都不知道
You guys are wrong. Yes,there is a chronological age difference.
不过你们都错了 没错，我们是有年龄上的差异
But I never notice it, because she is very mature.
但是我都感觉不到 为什么？因为她很成熟
It doesn't matter what you guys think. I'm dating Elizabeth, not you.
况且我根本不在意你们的看法 跟她交往的是我，不是你们
Not what she said last night.
她昨晚可不是这么说的
See,now,he could date her.
他配她就够幼稚
Will you marry me?
你愿意嫁给我吗？
Hey, you marry me.
嫁给我
-What's going on, little elves? -It's the big night. We wish you luck.
-怎么了，小精灵们？ -今晚很重要，我们想祝你好运
-You have the ring? -In my pocket.
戒指带了吗？ 就在口袋里
-Phoebe. -Wha..?
菲比
Will you guys get out of here? This is a surprise.
麻烦你们出去 我想给她惊喜，她会看出来
Yeah,you guys. Get out of here.
没错，快出去
Hey,guys.
你们好
-You look beautiful. -Thank you.
-你好漂亮 -谢谢
What's going on?
怎么了？
We're just really...
我们只是…
excited about this charity event we have to go to.
要参加慈善晚会觉得很兴奋
-Here. -Thank you.
给你 谢谢
-So, what's going on here? -Well,this is a silent auction.
-现在是怎样？ -这是一场不喊价拍卖会
They lay the stuff here. You write down your offer.
要卖的东西都在这里 你写下竞标价
Then the highest bid gets it.
出价最高的就是得主
I know what a silent auction is. What's going on with your hair?
我知道什么叫不喊价拍卖会 我是说你的头发怎么了？
-Why? -No,it's nice.
-怎么说？ -不是啊，很好看
Nice to see you. So glad you brought someone.
欢迎 你带了一位朋友来
Someone? I brought people.
一位？我带了两位
Phoebe, this is Mr. Thompson. He's the head of my department.
菲比，这位是汤普森先生 他是我的部门主管
-And I also brought my friend Joey. -Shrimp toast!
-我还带了我的朋友乔伊… -虾子吐司
You know, I don't know where he is.
我不知道他在哪里
I hope you'll bid.
希望你会参加竞标
Actually,I was about to bid on this lovely trip to Paris.
我正打算投标这趟巴黎之旅
-Nice choice. Good luck. -Thank you.
-有眼光，祝你好运  -谢谢
Okay.
好
Twenty dollars.
20元
Shut the door! Shut the door!
把门关上，把门关上
-What's going on? -Guys are throwing water balloons.
-怎么了？ -对面的男生在朝我们丢水球
Call the cops. That's what I did to kids in my building.
你们得报警 我都这样对付我家那栋的小孩
No, it's a water balloon fight. We started it.
这是水球仗，是我们挑起的
I stopped by to see if you wanted to see this play tonight.
听我说 我来问你晚上要不要去看戏
It's excellent. The director is..
这出戏应该很棒，导演…
-Who drank all the kamikazes? -Nobody. We put them in here!
-谁把神风特攻队都喝了？ -没有，在水球里
You want some?
你要吗？ 不要
-Could I talk to you for a second? -Yeah,sure.
我可以跟你讲一下话吗？ 当然可以
So this play, what do you think?
所以你要去看戏吗？
-It's gotten great reviews.. -Attack!
-它的剧评很好…  -攻击！
-Put your balloons down! -You put your balloons down!
-放下水球 -你们才放下
Everybody put their balloons down!
统统都把水球放下
Now,this is a nice suit!
这可是高级西装
If you'll excuse us...
请你们出去一下
I would like to speak to Elizabeth alone for a moment.
我要单独跟伊丽莎白谈谈
Whoa,Liz. Your dad's a bummer.
丽莎，你爸好扫兴
Our next item is the romantic trip to Paris.
下一项拍卖品是巴黎浪漫之旅
It goes to Emil Alexander with a high bid of $2300.
由艾弥尔亚历山大 以2千3百元的高价得标
So close!
只差一点
Guys,look. Got me some drinks.
你们看，我拿了几杯酒
-What are you doing? -Open bar.
-你在干什么？ -不用钱嘛
Well,now it's an empty bar.
你会把人家喝垮
You can't stand anyone else enjoying themselves, can you?
你就是见不得别人开心对吧？
Finally,our biggest item.
最后是今晚的最大项目
The 22-foot Gentleman's Daysailer sailboat.
22尺豪华帆船
The winning bid was a whopping $20,000.
得标金额高达2万元
I won.
我赢了
That was my guess.
那是我猜的
-What? What? What? -I guessed $20,000.
-什么？ -我猜2万
Joey,it is an auction. You don't guess. You buy!
乔伊，这是拍卖会 你不是猜，是买
What?
什么？
I don't have $20,000.
我没有2万
Congratulations on your new boat, Joey Tribbiani.
恭喜你购得新船… 乔伊崔比亚尼
Joey,sit down.
坐下啦
Forget her. You enjoy this.
别理她，开心就好
What are you doing?
你在干什么？
"One nation...
一个国家
under God,indivisible, with liberty and justice for all."
在神之下 不可分割，全民拥有 自由公正
I remembered it. The champagne is here.
我记得是这样背，香槟来了
-You okay? -Yes. I'm good. Are you good?
-你没事吧？ -我很好，你好吗？
Is everything..? Are you perfect?
这一切…你很好吗？
Yeah. I'm okay.
还好
Actually,I'm a bit cold. Can I have your jacket?
其实我有点冷 外套可以借我吗？
No, you can't have my jacket.
不行，我的外套不能借你
Because then I would be cold.
因为那样我就会冷
If you thought you'd be cold, you should've brought a jacket.
你要是觉得会冷 应该自己带外套
But, other than that, are you okay?
除此之外你好吗？
-Are you sure you're okay? -Yes. I'm fine.
-你真的没事吗？ -对，我很好
In fact,I've been fine for a long time now and I think...
我这段日子一直都很好 我觉得…
the reason is you.
都是因为有你
That's sweet.
好甜蜜喔
Before I met you, I had really little life.
认识你之前 我的人生微不足道
-And I couldn't imagine growing old.. -Oh,my God.
-我无法想像一个人… -我的天哪
-I know. But let me say it. -Richard.
-我知道，不过让我说完  -理查
What? I'm Chandler.
什么？我是钱德
Oh, that's Richard.
那是理查
Maybe he won't see us. Richard!
也许他会没看见 理查
Monica. Chandler.
摩妮卡，钱德
I don't know why I did that.
我不知道我为什么要抱你
-Good to see you. -You too. You let your hair grow.
-见到你真好 -彼此彼此，你把头发留长了
That's right. You always wanted me to.
没错，你一直希望我留长
-I see your mustache is back. -Well,my nose got lonely.
-你又开始留胡子了 -我的鼻子感到寂寞
You don't have a mustache, which is good.
你没留胡子，很好
Chandler. I make jokes when I'm uncomfortable.
我是钱德，我一蹩扭就开玩笑
-Hi,I'm Lisa. -Hi.
我是丽莎
I'm sorry. Lisa, Monica, Chandler. We used to date.
抱歉，丽莎 摩妮卡，钱德 我们交往过
Richard, no one's supposed to know about us.
理查，我们的事应该保密
See? I did it again.
我又来了
-Chandler,sit down. -I'll sit down.
-钱德，我们坐下吧 -好，我坐
-Good to see you. -Your table's ready,sir.
-很高兴见到你  -您的桌子准备好了
Good to see you guys.
很高兴遇见你们
If you prefer,this table's available.
这一桌也是空的
That might be fun.
一起坐应该不错
-What were you thinking? -I didn't know it was an auction.
你在想什么？ 我不知道这是拍卖会
I figured I'd take a guess. Help a charity. Free boat!
我以为是猜一猜 帮助慈善团体，免费得帆船
Why would a charity give away a boat?
慈善团体为什么要送帆船？
I don't know. Charity?
我哪知，做慈善吗？
Well,just buy the damn boat.
你就买吧
Don't you think you've had enough to drink?
菲比，你喝得够多了吧？
I'm just helping the kids.
我只是在帮助儿童
How is you drinking helping the kids?
你喝酒怎么能帮助儿童？
Because the more I drink, the less there is for the kids to drink.
我喝得越多 孩子们能喝的就越少
Mr. Tribbiani, your contribution brings us...
崔比亚尼先生 你的慷慨解囊
a step closer to building the youth center.
让兴建活动中心的事大有进展
-I'm so happy you brought him. -So am I.
-我很高兴你带他来 -我也是
I'm curious. How much is that boat worth?
我很好奇，那艘船值多少？
-I think it was valued at 19,000. -Hey,I was pretty close.
-差不多是1万9  -我猜得蛮准的
So,bad news.
坏消息
I can't buy the boat. I don't have any money.
我不能买那艘船，我没有钱
Joey! Joey, good one. He's silly.
乔伊，你真幽默
Good! Very good!
你真会演
-So I think I'm gonna take off now. -You can't leave,Joey!
-好吧，我要闪了 -你不能走，乔伊
You agreed to buy that boat. It's a contract.
你答应要买船，具有约束力
Plus,if you leave, my boss will kill me.
而且你走了 我的主管会宰了我
I don't have that kind of money.
那怎么办？我没有那么多钱
I know. Okay,okay. This is what we'll do.
我知道，好 好 这样吧
We'll let the next highest bidder buy it.
我们去找出价第二高的人 然后让他们去买
Then you'll pay the difference.
你只要付差价
Okay. I don't know why the kids need a youth center anyway.
好 这些小孩要活动中心干嘛
They should just watch TV after school like I did. I turned out fine.
放了学跟我一样看电视就好了 我现在也蛮好的
Not great.
但是不优秀
I'm helping the kids so much I think I'm gonna throw up.
我帮助贫童帮到想吐
So we're hiding in the bathroom...
我们躲在洗手间里
I get out. But before she can, her parents come in.
然后我溜出来 但摩妮卡还没出来 她父母就进去了
I hide in the shower. They start going at it on the floor.
于是我躲到浴帘后面 接着他们就在地上做起来了
Oh, my God!
我的天哪
I got a good one.
我有一个，我有一个
I once walked in on both my parents making love to the same guy.
我有一次撞见我父母 跟同一个男人做爱
It's so great seeing you guys again. I'd like to make a toast.
遇见你们真的好开心 我想敬酒
As a poet once said, "In the sweetness of friendship...
正如一位诗人所说 “在友谊的甜蜜里”
Let there be laughter and sharing of pleasures.
“尽情欢笑，分享欢乐吧”
In the dew of little things, the heart finds its morning and is refreshed."
“人心正是从中获得朝气 焕然一新”
What?
什么？
Oh,my God! You guys!
天哪，你们
Have we got a story for you. Guess who we bumped into?
在你开口之前，我们有事要说 猜我们吃饭时遇见谁？
-Who? -Richard!
谁？ 理查
Right, that's Richard's favorite place too.
没错，那里也是理查的最爱
-Oh,you knew that? Good. -Weren't you going out with Elizabeth?
所以你知道？很好 你不是要跟伊丽莎白约会？
I was. She was a little busy with a water balloon fight.
没错，但是她忙着打水球仗
Sometimes grownups have commitments they can't get out of.
有时大人就是会有事无法脱身
Maybe she is too young for me.
也许她真的太年轻了
When I was over there, I felt like I was a babysitter.
当我看到她跟朋友横冲直撞 我觉得我好像保姆
I see what you were talking about. I don't know what to do.
我终于开始了解你们的话 我不知道该怎么办
Weigh the good stuff about her against the bad.
你可以比较这段感情的利弊
That's what I did when I first started... weighing stuff.
我当初就是这样…比较东西的
Okay, bad stuff. I'm 12 years older than she is.
好，弊 我比她大12岁
The school could fire you.
学校发现会开除你
-She's leaving for three months. -For camp.
她要离开3个月 去参加夏令营
Okay, good stuff.
好，利
Well,she's sweet and pretty and..
她很甜很漂亮…
And the sex is probably great, huh?
性爱方面很赞吧？
It's tender and respectful, if that's what you mean.
如果你是指很温柔又互相尊重
The only thing you need to ask is, "Do you see a future?"
你只需要问你自己 你看得见未来吗？
Do you see yourself marrying her?
你能想像跟她结婚吗？
My God. You married her, didn't you?
天哪，你已经娶她了对不对？
No, I didn't do that. It's just...
没有啦，我只是…
Okay, honestly, no. I don't see a big future with her.
好吧，我觉得我们没什么未来
Okay, I think that's your answer.
那这就是你的答案了
I gotta talk to her. I hate this part.
我得告诉她 我最恨这个步骤了
Forget Elizabeth. If you're not careful...
你必须忘记伊丽莎白 你要是不小心
you may not get married at all this year.
今年可能会结不到婚
-Weren't you supposed to do something? -Good luck with Elizabeth,my man.
-你今晚不是要做某件事？ -祝分手顺利
My God, Phoebe, how many have you had?
天哪，菲比，你喝了几杯？
1,2,3... Seven times three.. 21!
一，二，三… 七乘以三，二十一杯
-You must be just wasted! -I'm a little tired.
-你一定醉翻了 -是有点累
-Next highest bidder is at table one. -Great.
出价第二高的人在一号桌 太好了
The guy with the Paris trip is at table four.
标到巴黎之旅的人坐四号桌
-Why do you care about who won? -It's a trip for two.
你干嘛管谁赢得巴黎之旅？ 那是双人之旅
Excuse me.
失陪
Is the person who won the Paris trip at this table?
抱歉，标到巴黎之旅的人 在这一桌吗？
-That was me. -Enchante.
我就是 真迷人
-Is there a Mr. Bowmont at this table?  -That's me.
抱歉，有没有一位波芒先生？ 我就是
Well,hello. This is your lucky day, Mr. Bowmont.
你好 你今天走运了，波芒先生
The Gentleman Daysailer has become available again...
那艘帆船又要卖了
and I believe you made a bid of $18,000.
你开了1万8的价格
You have to pay that. It's not just a guess.
你得付钱，不是猜好玩的
I was relieved I didn't win. My wife would've killed me.
我没标到船还松了一口气 我老婆会宰了我
You kidding? She'll love this boat!
不会吧？她会爱死这艘船
-What is your wife's name? -Pam.
尊夫人芳名？ 她叫潘
Just imagine this: The Pam.
只要想像一下 “潘之号”
I don't think she'd like that.
我想她不会喜欢
Okay. Imagine this: The Mr. Bowmont.
那想像…“波芒先生号”
-I don't think so. -Let me paint you a little picture.
还是不要了 让我为你描绘一下
You are setting sail up the Hudson. You've got the wind in your... arms.
你在哈德逊河上航行 风吹过你的头…双手
You get all that peace and quiet you've always wanted.
你得到你企盼已久的安宁
You get back to nature. You can go fishing.
你回到大自然怀抱 你可以钓鱼
You get one of those hats. People call you captain.
你可以买一顶帽子 让大家叫你船长
And then when you're old, Cappy.
等你老了就是老船长
-It's for a good cause. All right. -No way! It's mine!
-管他的，不买说不过去 我买了 -你别想，船是我的
What?
什么？
-The stuff you said,I want that! -But you don't have $20,000!
-你刚才说的那些事我也要 -但是乔伊，你没有2万
Who cares? I'll make payments! I want the Mr. Bowmont!
管他的，我分期，怎样都好 我要“波芒先生号”
-Oh,my God. You're back. -Let me see it. Let me see your hand.
-天哪，你们回来了 -让我看你的手，让我看你的手
Why do you wanna see my hand?
你为什么要看我的手？
I wanna see what's in your hand. I wanna see the trash.
我想看你手上拿的垃圾
It's all dirty. You should throw this out.
好脏，你最好拿去扔
-What did you just do? -What happened?
你们搞什么？ 怎么回事？
-Richard was there. I couldn't do it. -Oh,no.
理查也在，我无法开口 不会吧
I was gonna surprise her tomorrow.
我要延到明天，给她惊喜
-Now you've ruined it. -We didn't.
却被你们破坏了 我们没有
Who walks in a room and asks to see a person's hands?
谁会一进门就要看别人的手？
A palm reader, a manicurist, a hand doctor...
算命师、修指甲的小姐 手部医生…
-Glove salesman. -Good one!
手套推销员 漂亮
This is terrible. What will I do?
真惨，我该怎么办？
She only suspects something. So just throw her off the track.
她只是在怀疑，又不是确定 你可以唬她
I'll pretend marriage is the last thing on my mind.
也对，我可以让她觉得 我完全不考虑结婚
Yeah! Convince her you're scared of commitment, that you're a coward.
没错，让她相信你很害怕承诺 让她相信你有点孬种
I can do that. I've had years of practice.
我做得到，我练了30年
Being you is finally gonna pay off!
你这个人总算有价值了
Some idiot keeps stuffing the trash chute with pizza boxes.
某个白痴小孩老是用披萨盒 把垃圾槽堵住
That guy is still doing that?
那个砘锘故敲桓模
Oh,my God. Let me see your hand!
天哪，你们回来了 我看看你的手
You're too late! She already took out the trash!
来不及了 她已经把垃圾拿去扔了
Look,Elizabeth, we have to talk.
伊丽莎白，我们得谈一谈
I have never had such a healthy breakup.
我跟别人分手没这么平和过
She was such a grownup about it.
她表现得好成熟
She didn't seem too immature for me.
我觉得她一点也不幼稚
Did I just make a huge mistake?
我是不是犯了个大错？
Ross! Wait!
罗斯，等等
Elizabeth, thank God. I was just thinking about..
伊丽莎白，太好了 我正在想说…
You suck!
你最烂了
What?
什么？
Breakup's still on.
好，分手还是有效
Here she comes. Do I look like I don't wanna get married?
她来了 我像不像不想结婚的人？
And, also, a little like a French guy.
像，还有点像法国人
I never noticed that before.
我第一次发现
-What are you up to? -Hanging out. Talking about websites.
你们在干什么？ 只是在杀时间，聊网站
We saw this interesting website about marriage...
有一个网站在讨论婚姻...
and how unnecessary it is, a way for the government to keep tabs.
及婚姻的一无是处 说那只是政府监视你的方式
Yeah, Big Brother.
是啊，专制
That's a bit crazy.
有点夸张
Although I am glad you're looking at other things on the lnternet.
不过你们总算上了 其他类别的网站
Got me thinking. Why would anybody want to get married?
不过我就想 为什么会有人想要结婚？
To celebrate the relationship, solidify the commitment...
为什么？因为要赞颂这段感情 要巩固你们的承诺
declare your love for one another to the world.
要向全世界宣布你们的爱
Well,that's good to know.
能知道你的反应真好
The Mr. Bowmont is here!
“波芒先生号”来了
A diner wants to compliment you. Shall I let him in?
有一位客人想向主厨致意 要让他进来吗？
Sure. I love this part.
当然，我最爱这种事了
-Come on in. -Hi.
进来吧
-Richard. -I'm not here to compliment the chef.
理查  其实我不是来向主厨致意的
I hate when people come back to compliment the chef.
没关系 我最讨厌客人跑来致意
Like I have nothing better to do.
好像我很闲似的
So,what's up?
你有什么事？
It was great seeing you the other night.
那天晚上遇见你很开心
Good to see you too.
我也很开心
-You came to tell me that? -I came to tell you something else.
你就是来说这个的？ 不是，我是来说别的
I came here to tell you I still love you.
我是来说我仍然爱你
What? What did you..? What?
什么？你刚才…什么？
I still love you.
我仍然爱你
I know I shouldn't even be here telling you this.
我知道我甚至不该告诉你
You're with Chandler, who I like.
你跟钱德在一起，我很喜欢他
If you say he's straight, I'll believe you.
你说他是异性恋，我就相信你
After seeing you, I knew if I didn't tell you I'd regret it.
但见到你之后 我知道我不说会后悔一辈子
Letting you go was the stupidest thing I ever did.
放弃你是我所做过最蠢的事
You're really not supposed to be back here.
你不该到厨房来的
I'm sorry. I know this is the wrong time and the wrong place...
对不起, 我知道时机地点都不对...
but I had to tell you.
但是我一定要说
I wanna spend my life with you. I wanna marry you.
我想跟你共度一生，我想娶你
I wanna have kids with you.
我想跟你生儿育女
Oh,my God. Why don't they put chairs back here?
这里为什么没摆椅子？
Look,I know this is crazy, but am I too late?
我知道我很扯 已经来不及了吗？
You're too late. Where was all this three years ago?
没错 你3年前怎么不说这些话？
I know. I was an idiot.
我知道，我是个白痴
I tried to forget you. I really did.
我也想忘记你，真的
After our last lunch, I spent six months in Africa trying to forget.
我们去年吃完饭 我跑去非洲6个月想忘记你
-What did you do there? -Work with blind kids.
你去非洲做什么？ 帮助盲童
What are you doing to me?
你折磨我嘛
Look,I...
I'm sorry, but this is not gonna happen.
很抱歉，我们之间是不可能的
That's fine. I'll walk away. I'll never bother you again.
好，我会离开 再也不会来烦你
Only if you say Chandler's willing to give you everything I am.
但前提是 钱德也愿意给你这一切
Well,he is. I mean...
他愿意
marriage is all he talks about. My goodness!
没错，他成天把婚姻挂在嘴边
In fact, I'm the one making him wait.
事实上是我在让他等
You are? Why?
是吗？ 对
Why?
为什么？
Because of the government.
因为政府的阴谋
Isn't it incredible?
很棒吧？
Monica and Chandler are getting married.
摩妮卡和钱德要结婚了
I know. They'll be so happy together.
就是啊，他们会很幸福
How often do two best friends fall in love?
两个最要好的朋友坠入爱河 这种机率有多大？
-Not that often. -No.
并不太大 没错
-I'm so happy for them. -Me too. So happy for them.
我好替他们开心 我也是，好开心
I'm so happy and not at all jealous.
我很高兴，毫无嫉妒之心
Oh,no! God, definitely not jealous.
没错，当然没有
I'm probably 98% happy and maybe 2% jealous.
我可能是98%开心 2%嫉妒
-I mean,what's 2%? That's nothing. -Totally.
2%等于没有 没错
-I'm like 90/10. -Yeah. Me too.
我是九比一 我也是
Have you guys seen Chandler?
你们有见到钱德吗？
No. But you know who was looking for you?
没有，但你知道谁来找过你？
Tennille.
坦妮尔 （“船长与坦妮尔”为乐团）
The marriage stuff you were saying yesterday? You don't believe that.
你昨天说的那些话 应该不是真心话吧？
Sure,I do. In fact,I think the concept of marriage is unnatural.
当然是 事实上我觉得婚姻本身 就很不近人情
Look at pigs. Let's take a second here and look at pigs.
你看猪嘛，我们来看一下猪
Pigs don't mate for life.
猪不会有固定配偶
A pig can have 100 sexual partners in a lifetime.
猪的一生可以有一百个性伴侣
That's an ordinary pig, not even a pig that's good at sports.
那还只是普通的猪 而不是擅长运动的猪
Yeah, but that's pigs, not people.
对，但那是猪不是人
If marriage worked,I'd be for it. Do you know the divorce rate?
如果结婚行得通，我绝对支持 但是你知道美国的离婚率吗？
Ninety-seven percent!
97%
Wait a minute.
等一下
Are you telling me you may never want to get married?
你是说你可能永远都不想结婚
-Who's to say? -You! You are to say!
谁晓得？ 你啊，你晓得
Never say never, but, probably...
话不能说死，不过应该是…
yeah, never.
永远不会
Oh,my God. Then what are we even doing? What is this?
天哪，那我们在干什么？ 现在算什么？
Whoa,whoa,whoa! What is all this pressure?
干嘛对我施压？
Is this some new strategy?
这是某种新策略吗？
Why don't you put down your copy of The Rules, huh, mantrap?
你别再搞尔虞我诈那一套了
You know what? I gotta go.
你知道吗？我要走了
It's okay. I got a plan.
放心，我自有打算
-We're gonna find love. -Definitely.
我们会找到真爱的 一定会的
Yeah,I'm pretty confident about that.
我对这点有信心
That's what makes it so easy to be 80% happy for Monica and Chandler.
所以我可以有八成 替摩妮卡和钱德高兴
-A guarantee would be nice. -What do you mean?
不过要是有保障就好了 什么意思？
Some friends make a deal.
有些人不是会跟朋友约定
Like if neither of them are married by 40, they marry each other.
要是两个人到了40都没结婚 他们就要结婚
-A backup? -Exactly.
你是指备胎？ 没错
Yeah, I've got that.
我已经找好了
You do?
你找好了？
-Who? -Joey.
是谁？ 乔伊
-Joey? Are you serious? -I locked him in years ago.
乔伊？真的还假的？ 我好几年前就锁定他了
Wait. So if neither of you are married by 40, you'll marry Joey?
所以要是你们40岁还没结婚 你就要嫁给乔伊
Yep. We shook on it.
对，我们握手为定
But believe me, that is not how he wanted to seal the deal.
不过他可不想就此打住
Oh, seriously?
是吗？
I think his exact words were..
对，他说的是…
Charming.
真迷人
He's just a backup.
只是个备胎
-Hey,Monica. -Have you seen Rachel? Or a mirror?
-摩妮卡 -你有见到瑞秋吗？或是镜子？
-It's for my boat. Pretty cool,huh? -Yeah,it's great.
-这是我的船长装，酷吧？ -很酷
What's wrong? Talk to the captain.
怎么了？告诉船长
Just realizing I'm in a dead-end relationship.
我又发现这段感情是死路一条
-Chandler being difficult? -I don't want marriage tomorrow.
钱德欺负你是吧？ 我又不是明天就要结婚
But I wanna know we're going somewhere, that I'm not wasting time.
我只是想知道 我不是在原地打转，浪费时间
-You know Chandler. -No,I don't know Chandler.
你也了解钱德  我已经不了解钱德了
Not anymore. It's like something's changed.
仿佛有什么事变了
-Maybe you changed. -I didn't change.
也许是你变了？ 我才没变
Maybe that's the problem.
也许问题就在这里
-What? -Chandler is a complex fellow.
什么？ 钱德很复杂
One who is unlikely to take a wife.
不太可能成亲
Is that some kind of boat talk?
这是跑船人的用语吗？
I haven't totally decided how to talk on my boat yet.
我还没想好在船上的说话风格
Does he think I'll wait around for nothing?
他以为我会空等下去吗？
Face it. Chandler is against marriage.
面对现实吧，钱德反对婚姻
And always will be.
他是不会变了
There's some people who do wanna marry me.
有些人可是真心想娶我
-There are? -Yeah. Richard.
有吗？ 有，理查
Richard said he wants to marry you?
理查说他想娶你？
-And Chandler says he hates marriage? -That's right.
钱德说他痛恨婚姻？ 没错
Chandler loves marriage!
钱德热爱婚姻
You just said he hates marriage!
你刚才说他痛恨婚姻
"He's a complex fellow who's unlikely to take a wife"!
说他很复杂，不太可能娶妻
"He's against marriage and always will be"!
说他会永远反对婚姻
You got that from what I said?
你的解读是这样？
After the Cretaceous Period, the dinosaurs were gone.
白垩纪结束，恐龙也从此绝迹
What happened,you guys?
你们究竟怎么了？
-Rach. -Hey,you.
瑞秋 帅哥
-Come on in. -Thank you.
请进 谢谢
I'm so sorry to hear about you and Elizabeth.
很遗撼你跟伊丽莎白分手了
Thanks. I really thought we'd be able to make it work.
谢谢，我以为我们能克服万难
I guess it wasn't meant to be.
这大概是命中注定的
Yeah. Love. It's a tricky business,isn't it?
是啊，爱情…爱情真是微妙
-I guess so. -So,what do you say we make a pact?
是啊  我们要不要来做个约定
If you and I are both single by 40, we get married.
要是我们到了40都还没结婚 我们就结婚
I mean,we know each other, we like each other...
我们互相认识，互相喜欢
we've already slept together, so there'll be no surprises.
我们已经上过床，不会有意外
No, like, "What's that?"
不会觉得“搞什么？”
-Oh,you want me to be your backup. -Exactly.
你想找我当备胎？ 没错
Yeah. I already have one.
我已经有备胎了
-What? Who? -Phoebe.
是谁？ 菲比
Phoebe?
菲比？
But she just said Joey is her backup.
但是她说乔伊是她的备胎
Oh,I don't think so.
才不是呢
We just spoke. She said that she and Joey made a deal.
罗斯，我刚跟她聊过 她说她和乔伊约好了
That's impossible. We have had a deal for years. We shook on it.
不可能的，我们早就约好了 还握手为定
Although, believe me, she wanted to do a lot more than that.
只不过她觉得握手还不够…
Gunther, it's Joey. Is Chandler there?
阿甘，我是乔伊，钱德在吗？
Listen. What kind of muffins do they serve at sea?
我问你，跑船都吃哪一种松糕
Where the hell have you been?!
你上哪去了？
I was making a coconut phone with the Professor.
我在跟教授做椰子电话
Richard told Monica he wants to marry her.
理查跟摩妮卡说他想娶她
-What? -I've been trying to find you.
什么？ 就是啊，我一直想去找你 叫你别玩了
And I would have if these damn boat shoes wouldn't keep flying off!
可是这双鞋子跑一跑就掉
-Oh,my God! -I know! They suck!
我的天哪  就是啊，烂死了
He's not supposed to ask her to marry him! I am!
他不该向我的女朋友求婚 该求婚的人是我
-I know! -What..?
我知道 那…
You know what I'll do? I'll go over there and kick his ass!
你知道吗？我要去找他教训他
Will you help me?
你愿意帮忙吗？
Look, I don't think us getting our asses kicked is a solution, okay?
钱德，被他海扁一顿不是办法
-Look,just go and find Monica. -You're right.
赶快去找摩妮卡吧  你说得对
Okay. I'm gonna get the ring...
好 我去拿戒指...
I'm gonna go find her and I'm gonna propose!
我要找到她，直接向她求婚
Dude! Dude! Dude!
老兄 怎样？
That coconut phone might be good for the boat.
你的椰子电话 也许很适合摆在船上
Hi.
I don't know why I'm here.
我不知道我来干什么
I didn't ask.
我又没问
-You wanna come in? -I don't know.
你要进来吗？ 我不知道
Oh,okay.
好吧
I'll just leave the door open and sit on the couch.
那我把门开着，回去坐下
-Chandler is such an idiot! -Drink?
钱德真是个白痴  喝酒？
-Scotch on the.. -Rocks with a twist?
好，我要威士忌加… 冰块和莱姆片？
I remember.
我记得
You still smoking cigars?
还在抽雪茄？
No, no. That's art.
没有，那是艺术
If it bothers you, I can put my art out.
如果你不喜欢 我可以把艺术熄掉
No,that's okay.
没关系
So, Monica, let me ask you a question.
摩妮卡，我问你一件事
Since we broke up, do you ever...
我们分手后，你有...
think about me?
想过我吗？
Actually,I thought about you a few months ago.
我2个月前还想到你
-Really? -But it's because...
是吗？ 不过是因为...
I had an eye exam, and I don't like my new eye doctor.
我去做眼睛检查 又不喜欢我的新医生
-Who is it? -Edward Nevsky.
是谁？ 爱德华奈夫斯基
He's no good.
他的确很差
Do you ever think about me...
你有想过...
-in a non-eye-doctor way? -No.
非眼科医生的我吗？ 没有
Because getting over you was the hardest thing I've ever done.
但忘记你是我这辈子最难的事
I never let myself think about you.
我不让自己想到你
Wow.
Phoebe, you picked Joey and Ross?
菲比 你找了乔伊和罗斯？
-You can't have two backups! -Of course I can.
你不能有两个备胎 当然可以
It's good sense to back up your backup.
眼光独到才会替备胎找备胎
-Look, I've already lost Chandler. -What?
我已经折损钱德了 什么？
Hey, Phoebe! We're both your backup?
菲比，我们都是你的备胎？
How could you do this to me?
菲比，你怎么可以这样？
Why are you complaining? You were both aware of the situation.
我不知道你们在抱怨什么 你们都知道这个状况
-I was not! -No,we weren't!
我们不知道 我不知道
This kind of backtalk won't fly when we're married.
婚后你们可不能这样顶嘴
You can't have both. Pick one.
菲比，你不能独占他们 你得选一个
-Pick me! -No,pick me!
选我 不，选我
-I don't wanna end up an old maid. -All right. Well,let's see.
-我不想当老处女  -好吧，我看看
Ross is a good father.
罗斯是个好爸爸
But...
但是...
Joey has a boat. This is hard.
乔伊有船，好难选喔
This is crazy. I wanna switch to Rachel.
太扯了，我要换成瑞秋
-I wanna switch to Rachel too. -No,wait. Just wait.
我也要换成瑞秋  不，等一下
Wait,guys. Don't make any rash decisions.
你们别急着做决定
Just remember my promise:
记得我的承诺吧？
If we get married,three times a week.
结婚之后 1星期三次
Oh,my God. Phoebe...
天哪，菲比
I'm talking about massages.
我是说按摩
No,I'm not.
I know how to settle it. We'll do this.
我知道该怎么解决了 办法就是
I'm gonna write "Joey" on one napkin...
我在一张纸巾上写乔伊
and "Ross" on the other napkin and we're gonna pick one.
一张纸巾上写罗斯 然后我们一人抽一张
That person will be our backup. Okay?
那个人就是我们的备胎  好吗？
-Sounds fair. -All right.
很公平 那好
Good. Switching them up.
好，我来弄乱
-Pick one. -Left.
选一边 左边
-Thank you. -You're welcome.
谢谢 不客气
-Ross. -Joey.
罗斯 乔伊
-We should switch. -Absolutely.
我们交换好了 没错
I missed you, you ugly flat-faced old freak.
我想念你 丑不啦叽的扁脸老怪物
Excuse me?
你说什么？
Him.
他啦
I missed this apartment. Now, this is a grownup's apartment.
我想念这间房子 这才是大人的房子
I should be with a grownup, you know?
我应该跟大人在一起，你懂吧
You're saying you need to be with someone more mature.
你是说 你要跟比较成熟的人在一起
Maybe someone with...
也许是一个…
a license to practice medicine.
有医师执照的人
Or a mustache.
或是有胡子的人
Let's face it. I'm not a kid anymore.
说真的，我不是小孩子了
I need someone who wants the same things.
我需要一个目标相同的人
Coming to my work and telling me you love me, I want that!
来我工作的地方跟我示爱 我要的是那样
Talking about pig sex over lunch, I don't want that!
吃饭时聊猪的性爱 我不要那样
I think that's fair.
很公平
Fair? Please, don't even talk to me about fair.
公平？别跟我提公平
Fair would've been you wanting to marry me then.
公平的意思是你当年想娶我
Or Chandler wanting to marry me now.
或是钱德现在想娶我
Believe me,nothing about this is fair. Nothing.
这整件事一点也不公平
-Nothing! Nothing! -It's okay.
不公平不公平不公平… 别激动
Nothing.
不公平
I don't know.
我不知道
I know.
我知道
I have to figure some..
我得先...
Some stuff,before I can...
把事情想清楚 然后才能…
I understand.
我懂
Take as much time as you want.
你只管慢慢想
Ten, even 20 minutes, if you need it.
10分钟、20分钟都行
I'll be here. Not smoking.
我会在这里，不会抽烟
Where is she?
她人呢？
I'm not scared of you.
我可不怕你
She's not here. And please come in.
她不在，请进
Scotch on the rocks...
威士忌加冰和莱姆片
with a twist, on a coaster.
放在杯垫上？
Monica?
摩妮卡，摩妮卡
Okay, she was here. But she left.
好吧，她来过，又走了
Where did she go?
她去哪里？
She said she had to think things over.
她说她要想清楚
Oh,my God. I can't believe this. I thought you were a good guy.
天哪，我真不敢相信 我以为你是个好人
Look,nothing happened.
我们又没怎样？
Nothing? So you didn't tell my girlfriend you love her?
没怎样？那你没和我女朋友示爱？
Well, all right, one thing happened.
好吧，只有这样
You know what you did? My girlfriend is thinking things over.
我真不敢相信 你知道你做了什么？ 我的女朋友在想事情
You made my girlfriend think!
你让我的女朋友思考
Well,I'm sorry.
我很抱歉
-What's to think about? I love her. -Well...
她还需要想什么？我爱她
I'm willing to offer her things that you aren't.
我愿意给她你不愿意给的东西
I'm willing to offer her those things. I had a plan...
但是我愿意给 我只是故意...
to throw her off so when I offered all these things,she'd be surprised.
要让她失望 等真相大白，她就会很惊喜
If it helps, it worked very well.
那效果真的很好
It was working till you showed up, you big tree.
直到你杀出来，水泥墙
This isn't fair.
这样不公平
You had your chance with her, and you blew it!
你曾经有机会，结果你搞砸了
This is my chance. I won't blow it, because we are meant for each other.
现在轮到我了，我不会搞砸 因为我们是天生一对
And this has all just been one stupid mistake!
而这一切只是个愚蠢的错误
I was gonna propose tonight.
我本来打算今晚求婚的
-You were gonna propose? -Yeah,I even...
你要求婚？ 对，我还…
got a ring. Did you get a ring?
准备了戒指，你有吗？
No, I don't have a ring.
没有，我没准备
You go get her, Chandler.
你去找她吧，钱德
And can I give you a piece of advice?
我可以给你一个忠告吗？
If you do get her...
要是你得到了她
don't let her go.
一定要好好把握
Trust me.
相信我
You know, Richard, you are a good guy.
理查…你的确是个好人
I know.
我知道
I hate that.
真讨厌
-I've gotta find Monica. -She's gone.
待会再说，我得去找摩妮卡 她走了
-What? -She had a bag and she left.
-什么？ -她走了，提着一个包包走了
-What? -She was all crying...
-什么？ -她哭得很伤心
She said you guys want different things.
说你们要的东西不一样
-Why didn't you stop her? Why didn't you tell her it was a plan? -I told her everything.
-说她需要时间思考 你为什么不拦住她？ 不说出我的打算？ -我都说了
-But she wouldn't believe me. -Well,where..? Where did she go?
-但是她不信  -那她…她上哪去了？
To her parents'. She said you shouldn't call. But if I were you,I would.
她父母家，她叫你不要打给她 不过要是我就会打
-I can't believe I ruined this. -I am so sorry,man.
我居然搞砸了 我很遗撼
You wanted it to be a surprise.
你希望是个惊喜的
Oh,my God.
天哪
Chandler...
钱德…
in all my life...
我这辈子…
I never thought I would be so lucky...
从来没想过我会这么幸运
as to fall in love with my best...
可以…爱上我最要好的…
My best...
我最要好的…
There's a reason why girls don't do this! Okay, okay, okay.
所以说都是男人求婚嘛 好好好
I'll do it. I thought...
我来，我以为…
Wait, I can do this.
等等，我一定行
I thought that it mattered...
我以为...
what I said or where I said it.
开口的时间地点很重要
Then I realized...
后来才发现...
the only thing that matters is that you...
唯一重要的是你…
You make me happier than I ever thought I could be.
让我得到超乎想像的幸福
And if you let me...
所以如果你愿意
I'll spend all my life trying to make you feel the same way.
我愿意用下半生 让你跟我一样幸福
Monica...
摩妮卡…
will you marry me?
你愿意嫁给我吗？
Yes.
我愿意
I knew you were likely to take a wife!
我就知道你应该会成亲
Can we come in yet? We're dying out here!
可以进去了吗？我们快憋死了
Come in! Come in!
进来，进来
We're engaged!
我们订婚了
This is the least jealous I've ever been.
这是我最不嫉妒的时候
Oh, no, wait! This is wrong! Ross isn't here!
等等，不行啦，罗斯不在
Hell, he's done it three times. He knows what it's about!
他都玩三次了 知道是怎么回事